The classroom was supposed to be at the back,
for girls,
She couldn't find it.
I know some people who thought it was big,
I remember that.
and then the gates.
It's a source of both pride and sadness to see all this.
because it represents so much,
So much work.
Here we are in the ruins of the extraordinary building that was the Troyes sanatorium.
This building will soon be 100 years old.
since a large part of it was built between 1928 and 1932.
And this is the work of Maurice Violette, who was mayor from 1908 to 1960.
You see,
and he was a great builder.
All these children who fill the schools of large cities,
Look at them closely.
Listen to them too,
Listen to these disturbing things.
Look at these ashen faces.
Tuberculosis is everywhere.
Where in 1939 there were 10 cases of tuberculosis,
There are 15 of them today.
But to heal our children,
Beds will be needed in the beautiful countries where the joy of living is rediscovered in the modern era...
The great disease of the time,
It was tuberculosis.
We had nothing to treat her with,
simply to put people in the sun and to rest.
Since this disease was, in fact, quite contagious,
by spitting,
by so many things.
But we had nothing at the time.
So that's why...
that is to say, immediately after the war of 1914,
The mayor considered building a large complex.
something immense,
and they chose this wood which was called the wood of the mute woman.
The initial work,
It's going to be 1921.
and then little by little,
gradually,
We started with a display stand,
then a number of buildings,
huge buildings,
since there are three rows,
if I may say so,
and of which...
over 370 meters long and barely 10 meters wide,
because you only had rooms with good southern exposure and a corridor to go from room to room with,
Of course,
a number of other outbuildings,
if I may say so.
I'm sending you a photo of our new home.
Those were women who were there when the photo was taken.
because before,
It was a rest home.
NOW,
It's a sanatorium.
My room is marked with a cross.
and the bed you see,
It's mine.
There are two women per room.
and I have a radio to keep me entertained.
How sad!
We used to come here in the 1950s.
Oh yes,
back then I was very young,
I was...
Well, we weren't very tall either.
We were still in kindergarten with Jean-Luc.
Yeah...
My father was the city architect.
My dad won the competition.
Because in fact,
There had been a competition for the design of the sanatorium.
And so,
the mayor at the time,
Maurice Violette,
He trusted him.
And he was the one who designed the entire preventorium building.
of the sanatorium.
That is to say, there was still a demand for
X rooms.
SO,
rather than doing a...
He preferred to build different types of buildings.
an alignment,
Finally, a composition.
So, there,
It was in his mind that the idea started to take shape.
I was very proud of it.
I was very proud of my dad.
Yet we didn't actually know each other.
Because he worked from midnight until 4 a.m.,
He was waking up,
He would have his little coffee in his bathroom, which my mother had prepared for him the day before, and that was that.
When you look at the architect's plans,
He often draws a shape resembling wind.
as if the wind were rushing in.
Because in order to treat the sick,
We also needed fresh air.
And so we often see all the...
Finally,
the wind,
He draws it like this.
If you zoom in on these shots,
and in fact,
I imagined it like that,
like a wind pattern that would come...
But anyway,
This is a personal interpretation and not necessarily the truth.
What I also liked about those balconies,
It was the little details.
Are there still places where we can climb or not?
Because I see that quite a few shutters have fallen.
It's so great to be here after all this time.
It's beautiful nonetheless.
Which is very funny,
It's that in the organization of the buildings...
What I find interesting,
that's the very first one,
the one in front,
truly towards the grand landscape
It was the pavilion of people who had money.
It's really very well done.
Afterwards,
there was the pavilion,
the second,
who was,
I believe it was the poor.
those who didn't necessarily have the means to pay,
so those who were not on the front line.
There was none,
them,
the wide, unobstructed view.
And then,
That's very cynical.
But then,
the last one,
It was the one for the very, very sick.
Later,
the children's pavilion was added in the second phase.
But those who were very...
sick and right behind was the crematorium.
In fact, it's the modernism plan.
In the foreground are those who had money, then we move further away, and the sicker you are, the more you go towards the crematorium, you know.
The shape,
the function there,
We're there.
I graduated from Paris-Malaquais, completing my diploma at the Dreux sanitarium.
And so I found this one because it combined quite a few criteria that I found interesting.
The entire aspect of the modernist plan,
etc.
But also on all those details of 1930s Art Deco,
which I liked very much,
It's an era that I really appreciate.
And there are plenty of details that we don't necessarily pay attention to.
But it's going to be all these little forms of wind,
the wind rushing in.
At the level of the facades,
We're going to look at some small details.
We have railings that are very typical of the 1930s and especially the letters on the pavilions which are very typical and which I found very interesting.
That was the cover of my dissertation.
What interested me and the aspect I worked on,
It was programmatic obsolescence.
That is to say, sanatoriums,
like other buildings,
are built for a specific purpose.
That's the genius of these buildings,
That's because we build them to meet a need.
Here,
it was about defeating tuberculosis when vaccines didn't exist.
And so,
These are buildings with very unusual shapes.
which at least made it possible to treat the sick.
So,
it was in the open air,
exposure to light,
etc.
And so,
these are buildings which,
due to their typological aspect,
They are very difficult to maintain today.
to renovate,
since the vaccines were discovered,
and also that we no longer have any use for those buildings.
And so,
They are left to decay.
and for some,
for many years.
Alas,
Hitler is hungry.
During an election campaign a year ago,
We warned you,
friends,
that there was nothing to be done with fascism.
However, you wanted to trust him.
We were warmongers.
Today,
You can see that clearly,
Hitler will always be hungry.
Maurice Violette,
August 30, 1939
When the Germans approached Dreux in June 1940,
the director of the sanatorium,
a baradier doctor,
has run away,
shouting "every man for himself",
And he disappeared.
leaving his patients at the sanatorium stranded.
And so we called my stepfather in a panic.
And that is why he arrived in Dreux very quickly and settled in the doctor's house.
I don't know if it was that one.
That was the administration.
I think his offices were there.
During the Second World War,
The Germans were really scared,
if I may say so
The chances of getting sick and catching tuberculosis were not too high.
of these buildings,
This allowed Dr. Roche to be able to hide Jews or resistance fighters.
Dr. Roche and his wife altered patients' X-rays at night and falsified test results.
Well, that's it.
when I learned about it,
It really...
There were obviously sick people too,
I was going to say there were real sick people in that sanatorium.
obviously.
But at the time, we were analyzing spit.
And so my stepfather changed the name on the samples that were taken from the patients.
And when the Germans demanded proof as to whether the Jews were actually sick,
Jewish doctors in particular,
I'm thinking of Dr. Edner.
because my stepfather had talked to me about it a lot.
A day,
I was resting,
And I was still worried.
I knew that at any moment,
The weapons could arrive.
And I heard "boom,
boom.
And I knew,
I was trying on some Germans.
They came looking for me.
another.
There was another one,
I was hiding there.
And then,
I have some...
“Dr. Hegner,
"Yes?" I told him, "Look,
"Pack your suitcase"
And he made a phone call.
At the Gestapo,
he said, but there,
the doctor we had gone to get,
He has tuberculosis.
It is contagious.
He was able to stay in the sanatorium.
The Germans came back for him a second time.
Again,
The fact that he was always positive is what made him come back.
He went back to the sanatorium.
Moreover, it's also dry.
and there,
That's when he remembered an acquaintance.
where he crossed,
Someone came to visit,
a lady he had cared for in the past,
and he asked her if he could disappear to her house.
They never stated this in our presence.
in front of their children
of their activities.
that they had in a resistance network called Libération Nord.
And in fact,
This is Dr. Jean Baudvinic.
a doctor from Dreux,
who discovered this because he was searching for people who had helped Jews during the war.
And that's absolutely incredible.
Finally,
it was an absolutely incredible discovery for the whole family,
for their children
for their grandchildren,
and especially since they had disappeared.
And that was the only thing we knew,
That's what my mother-in-law told me, saying,
Yes, indeed, during the war radios were falsified.
We changed the analyses.
It was very...
She saw that,
I wouldn't say it was just for fun.
but it gave him,
It certainly gave them both a great deal of satisfaction.
That's impressive.
As you can see,
This place is absolutely huge.
Many staff members were very attentive in order to do everything they could.
obviously to protect the sick and the Jews, naturally.
There must have been at least sixty people working for the children.
At the sanatorium,
There must have been two or three hundred people working for the sanatorium.
Among these two or three hundred people,
There were resistance fighters.
Who were they?
We don't really know.
What was their relationship with each other?
We don't really know either.
But of course there were cells that were not necessarily in contact with each other.
And that was also the code of silence.
And we knew about it.
And the better it was.
Finally,
if we can say so,
There were a few people who benefited from this welcome,
but we cannot say that there were many or not many.
The only traces to truly speak,
historically speaking and in reality,
We need to have written records somewhere.
even testimonies, possibly
but real testimonies from people who have experienced this, and not just rumors.
I heard that 300 Jewish children were saved at the Preventorium.
That's completely false.
There were indeed 300 children at the time of the collapse,
led by the two schoolteachers when the Germans arrived,
but there were never 300 Jewish children at the Preventorium.
We lived in Dreux.
I started having breathing problems.
We went to the doctor.
they told us,
You have tuberculosis.
We need to send you to the sanatorium in Dreux.
Then I unfortunately infected my brother,
my sister,
And the three of us ended up here.
Me with my brother and sister with the girls.
And now, do you remember what that was or not?
Oh no, I don't know what that was.
Well, we were only there once.
We passed through once in one direction.
once in the other.
That's what we're doing today.
There was an operating room,
but perhaps there,
I wasn't.
The refectory was there.
There,
were the spa treatments.
it was the dormitory world.
Come on,
the slur was there.
We were passing by there,
and we would go to the shower.
It reminds me of the veterans right now who are visiting the sites where they landed 80 years ago.
I feel like I'm doing the same as them.
that I return,
but not on a war site.
I unfortunately returned here in 1951.
in October,
and I got out a year later.
in October 1952.
There were about 35 of us children.
Of
8 years at
15 years old,
I was the oldest one, by the way.
I was too young to go to the men's ward,
and I could only go to the children.
When I first arrived,
There were about forty of us.
no more.
maximum.
And then,
Some have found themselves cured.
When I went out,
There were only 25 or 30 of us left.
The first day,
when we arrived here,
When I told you at the entrance,
It was marked "entered on such and such a day".
died on such and such a day.
It didn't happen like that for me.
When we arrived here,
We were first given a sputum aspiration to examine the sputum.
if we were still infected and all that.
And then,
We were given treatment.
It was pasignacide and rémifond,
which still exist
I believe.
and then...
Since I wasn't healing quickly,
I had a pneumothorax.
So, pneumothorax,
Air is insufflated between the pleura and the lung.
in order to shrink the affected lung.
I had injuries,
I had two lesions,
So I had the pneumothorax for almost two and a half years.
Once I got out,
I was getting breaths at the dispensary in Dreux.
Every two weeks,
We needed to be given more air so that our lungs would remain contracted.
so that it can heal.
It was a dormitory,
There were 40 beds,
There were baffles between each bed,
small squeaky toys.
There,
at the beginning,
when I arrived,
There were 38 of us.
something like that,
with an adobre.
And in the morning,
There was the toilet,
then breakfast.
So there was a refectory,
The girls on one side,
the boys on the other side.
All this under the supervision of Sister Maria.
And there were five maids.
There was already a school.
There was a school for girls,
Finally, a classroom for girls on one side and boys on the other.
which was run by Mr.
and Mrs. Dubost.
After that came the treatments,
Afterwards there was lunch and then we went back to the spa.
So you had to stay lying on your back,
to do nothing.
One could read,
things like that,
But we mustn't move.
We mustn't move.
You should stay on your back as much as possible.
What were you reading?
We weren't allowed to read.
I don't remember anymore.
At that time, people read Tintin comics,
Spirou,
Things like that.
It wasn't the sister who lent us books.
At
the age of 4,
I was diagnosed with a fairly significant primary infection.
So at the time,
There were quite a few people with tuberculosis.
Places like this,
immense,
pretty much everywhere in France.
And me,
I was put in this sanatorium.
Because people,
They didn't want to come near us.
because it's very contagious.
If you send spittle to someone,
that you have tuberculosis.
We talked about Covid,
But that was huge at the time.
I have several aunts who died at 17.
And all the families,
rich or poor,
There were tuberculosis patients.
To get me to come here,
My father told me a story, saying that we were going into the forest,
in a beautiful location
to see deer.
We might bring one home,
especially in a Parisian apartment
That would have been pretty good.
That's not bad.
I think so.
And then,
SO,
I arrived here.
And then,
Of course,
I realized I was going to stay there.
There was a little girl who was very pale,
who must have been 8 years old,
maybe.
And then,
I approached,
But we didn't speak to each other.
She always did that to me.
And I,
I sat down on the ground.
And then we looked at each other like that,
I loved it.
I thought she was beautiful.
like a little elf.
Then I thought to myself,
I might still go see Bambi, closer to her.
or things like that.
I have a lot of imagination.
And then one day,
I haven't seen it since.
And besides, I was still keeping my ear to the ground.
I hear instructors saying, "Oh well, you know,
the little one... »
I don't know what they called him next door.
"She left last night."
Without understanding,
I did understand, though, that I wouldn't see her again.
The morning,
We had a café au lait or a kind of hot chocolate with milk.
but instead of bowls,
They were like the bowls we give to dogs now.
So, a little girl,
How do you want it?
then either with a tablespoon,
Or else you had to take the bowl and do that.
And then we had slices of bread and butter.
And then there were large ones,
We often put smaller ones next to larger ones so that the larger ones could take care of them.
And the big ones,
Sometimes,
they would steal our sandwiches.
And on Sundays,
So we had visitors.
We were given less to eat because they knew that the parents brought treats.
And then in the evening,
every Sunday,
It was the same thing.
They gave us pudding.
And then, this...
I loved it though.
But that's all we had to eat.
supposedly,
because the parents had brought sweets.
Dear Auntie,
Dear Uncle,
I'm doing well.
I eat well.
I think you're doing well.
We went to the cinema on Sunday.
I'm resting well.
We build wooden cabins.
I am in good health.
I send you my warmest regards.
So,
the essence of cinema,
I loved it.
Of course,
but it was all in black and white.
SO,
as a film,
They were often rather sad films.
So,
there were the two orphans,
I don't remember whose it is.
That.
Anyway,
But anyway,
That makes me...
And the film that made everyone laugh,
it was
François I with Fernandelle.
So,
there was a passage.
Phew,
Ferdandelle,
He is lying down.
We're going to torture him.
That's a joke.
What.
They put salt on his feet and a goat licks his feet.
She's going to make him...
For me,
it wasn't funny.
I had the impression that he was suffering.
Here is the X-ray image of the boy.
Unfortunately, this confirms the previously established diagnosis.
The child has tuberculosis.
His good health is only apparent.
This round cavern is the typical lesion of childhood tuberculosis.
Well,
radio is nothing.
Breathe,
Breathe more.
Because we had tuberculosis.
Regular testing was necessary.
And then,
They're doing a tubing analysis for you.
At the time,
when I was 4 years old,
the pipe was like this.
And they pinched my nose.
And then you had to open your mouth.
and the tube passed all the way to the stomach to collect the mucus.
Mucus,
We analyze them to see if there are still what are called BKs present.
shell bacilli.
But like the little ones...
At the time, people didn't let themselves be pushed around.
They put us in a straitjacket,
like in a madhouse.
SO,
a 4-year-old girl,
when we do that to him,
We don't really understand.
We were made to write,
But I didn't know how to write.
So it's a monitor who's writing,
So I wrote to my dad that I wished him a Merry Christmas and that for the Christmas holidays I was going to be dressed up as a little dwarf.
Dear Dad,
I am still in good health and I think the same is true for you.
Yesterday,
The cinema was very interesting.
We watched a film about the mountain.
We are...
In the midst of preparations for the Christmas festivities,
I am a little dwarf.
Do you see?
The little mountain dwarves,
Greenish greens,
They work all night,
While the shepherds sleep.
That's all I remember!
Tuberculosis still kills 10,000 French people every year.
It is therefore important to educate the public,
from school onwards, but also afterwards,
ways to avoid it and defend against it.
Hence the importance of information and health education in this area.
It is on this theme that the new anti-tuberculosis stamp campaign, presented by Georges Duhamel, has just been launched.
President of the National Committee for the Defense against Tuberculosis,
to Mr.
Chenot,
Minister of Public Health.
It is probably primarily a place of medical memory.
since until the arrival of streptomycin in the 1950s,
It completely dethroned what was called heliotherapy.
that it was the sun that was supposed to kill the BK,
the body bacillus,
the tuberculosis bacillus.
From the moment streptomycin came into existence,
The sanatorium was no longer very useful.
and so it was disinfected.
replaced by other services.
These buildings reserved for tuberculosis patients will gradually become useless after having at times received more than 1000 patients.
And so it will be transformed first.
In specialization,
a cardiac hospital,
cardiology
then after a nursing home.
But in 1995,
This building will be completely emptied.
if I may say so,
and it will gradually become a ruin.
One of my friends,
I don't know if he was squatting or renting.
but lived here.
I remember small fairs,
meals,
of some rather strange things we did here.
Finally,
odd, aren't they?
But at the time it was great because you could walk around the corridors,
We took some photos.
We did a lot of things.
And it's true that it was interesting because it wasn't in that state.
There were still windows.
It wasn't a drafty hotel.
And so we had the opportunity to do scavenger hunts,
to do lots of things.
It was magical.
For me, it's about having fun.
It's not the illness or anything like that.
For me, it's the festive side.
That's the fun side of it.
It's the hide-and-seek aspect that we could play.
Because here it's magical.
We hadn't come.
with the aim of taking photos, which is why the photos,
Okay, these are really just quick, hastily taken photos; they're photos that represent...
We can see the corridors,
You can still see that there were beds in some of the photos; there's one I remember, it's in my friend's kitchen.
It must be said that we had
24-25 years old.
We're joking,
We're having fun.
It's true that it's a time when everything is cool.
There is no stress.
There is no AIDS.
There's nothing there.
Life lies ahead of us.
life is beautiful.
We learn it with passion,
with desire.
2022,
Always the blues.
Okay.
I see 2022.
So there are people who came in 2022.
Most of the time,
when I finished classes and we had gaps in our schedules,
We used to come here to spend some time before taking the bus back home.
And generally people came to visit the place and sometimes even climb onto the roofs.
We were having fun,
we were doing a little bit of...
So, we were free here, so we had fun when we came.
For me it was a big building that you could visit and run around in.
That was actually the goal.
Actually,
There's that building there,
We have two hours left to go.
Okay then, come on, let's go to the other one.
And in fact, we were going as fast as possible to really visit all the buildings.
In fact, we were in far too much of a hurry.
We wanted to discover everything right away.
And we had discovered practically everything in two days.
We had looked at everything and then we saw some magnificent rooms.
like the theatre hall,
which was a room where people would sit and relax.
We would sit there,
We played in it.
So it was a place that was very important to us.
And then we'll have a memory of it that will be more than positive.
Young people like it.
to come to abandoned places.
It's a little extra something.
It gives you a little bit of an adrenaline rush.
Let's say.
Here too,
It has doubled.
we know that we can see clearly,
They are young people.
They threw things away.
There,
we have a nice graph.
You see what,
You ?
Okay,
come on,
We're going to go and make the other two butterflies.
the theatre,
All of that.
For me,
it's really on the main road,
the theatre.
Eh ?
What is it?
We weren't bothering anyone and we were having a good time with friends.
The water tower,
We arrived with friends after class.
There were several of us.
So we went all the way to the top.
We had taken a photo to immortalize the moment, but we haven't been able to find it again.
Unfortunately.
This is a moment of freedom.
we were up there,
We sat down,
We discussed,
We stayed put up there and didn't move.
Then we went back down because it was still quite scary.
That's exactly the one.
Me,
when I came after high school,
that hole,
He wasn't there.
So, seeing that,
Yes,
That pisses me off.
Actually,
Let's just say I'm nostalgic about having come and having...
I actually liked the idea of ​​the place, but I'm actually disgusted because I see they were there more and more, and again, seeing people who are going to redo the work there, building houses... I can't believe it.
I tell myself, I tell myself it's not possible, when you see the walls, when you see the ceiling, everything is dead, actually
Oh yes,
There,
it could be likened to a small room,
Here too.
But there are some,
They are gigantic.
Which is very funny,
It's because about ten years ago,
I had fun looking up which monuments in Drôme were the most visited on the Internet.
What was most searched for on the Internet,
It was the sanatorium.
It wasn't the Belfry,
It was not the Royal Chapel,
But it was that building that had this reputation for being haunted.
etc.
But unfortunately...
Well,
I don't think I have the exact date anymore.
But a 19-year-old boy fell down the stairs and was killed.
And of course,
there,
Everything has changed.
There was definitely a before and an after.
Ahead,
We were doing well.
We were filled with positivity when we arrived.
And then after his death,
We came back much later to pay our respects and also to see the building one last time.
And from there,
Right away, actually, it's a burden.
We don't feel very comfortable there.
We even went back at night.
It was even worse.
We really weren't comfortable there at all.
This building, however, is for those who will live here.
Clearly, those who believe in ghosts aren't going to like this.
We are in a place,
It's true that there's a story behind it.
It's a sanatorium.
It's a place that is impressive in its scale.
its grandeur,
And it's a dark place.
We go for a walk at night.
we want to,
In fact,
often these are old houses,
One is tempted to say that it is haunted.
when it's an old hospital,
You'd almost say it's haunted.
For now, I...
In any case,
in all my experiences here,
I have some doubts at times.
But I can never,
In any case,
I cannot confirm that this place is actually haunted.
And I'm very sorry about that.
I came,
I visited the place in a sort of urban exploration style.
So really just the visit.
I don't really have a camera,
I had a phone,
I had...
There.
And I visited and...
I could hear noises,
I was hearing things and then all that.
Obviously,
when you are all alone in such a large place,
We ask ourselves a lot of questions.
And then,
we realize that in fact,
between what we see in videos and what we see in real life,
These are two different things because our brain is working extremely hard.
Our brain,
our eyes,
Everything is working.
And yet,
There are things that caught my attention.
I was hearing things like...
A small voice, but it was really a film.
It was light.
And it was from that moment that I thought it would be a good idea to get a camera.
I just come and that's it.
So we come with equipment,
So we come with our cameras.
We come with digital recorders,
We come with lots of little objects that for us...
allows one to try,
to test things.
It's not an exact science,
So we're feeling our way a little bit,
We're trying lots of things to try and get an answer.
to try to have communications that can take place.
We are here to try to communicate with you.
with the people who remained in that building.
We're not here to break things,
We're not here to steal.
We are here with complete goodwill.
So we expect from you,
This is a sign of your presence.
It could be a noise,
It could be about touching us.
It could involve using the different instruments that we will offer you.
We're going to have that little fear, though.
There is a twofold fear.
The common fear is that, indeed,
there is something paranormal going on.
and that we don't know how to react.
As for the second fear,
that there are people there,
or law enforcement officers who surprise us in a place that is,
(in parentheses)
anyway,
Nevertheless,
forbidden.
Could you try repeating my first name?
Please ?
My name is Mickey.
Can you try to repeat Mickey?
I've had two experiences,
at least here,
that made an impression on me.
The first,
It's with cards.
I was playing with cards, saying,
What is this card?
It was an ace of spades that I held in my hand.
We use a machine called a spirit box,
It's a radio that scans radio waves.
We can hear the radio.
That's where it's always complicated to make a definitive statement in the end.
and to know what percentage chance,
or what is the probability of having an intelligent answer.
And at that moment,
That clearly answered this topic.
Have you understood the rule?
I'll show you the first card.
It's not the most haunted place in France,
because,
as I said,
Each investigation is very complicated.
There is a complexity in every investigation.
No matter where it is,
There is always a different level of complexity.
In this case,
It's open.
Even years ago,
It was open.
So there are ambient noises,
There is,
I just heard a noise.
I think it's a shooting range or something.
So in my opinion, it was gunshots.
So during the day,
There are ambient noises that are omnipresent.
At night,
There are also the animals, which are omnipresent.
So there are all kinds of animals roaming the world.
the woods,
all of that,
There.
SO,
finding things that are actually paranormal,
It's very complicated.
To say that this is the most haunted place in France,
That's wrong.
That's completely false.
The hospital will sell to the town hall for a symbolic one franc.
and the town hall will be left with its buildings in ruins.
not really knowing what to do with it.
A number of projects have been undertaken,
to turn it into an aquatic center,
a training center for somewhat niche sports,
like the crossbow,
like shooting,
etc.
And then the buildings will therefore interest real estate companies to turn them into apartments in the woods.
And I think there were roughly
100 million will be spent to renovate nearly 300 apartments.
Can you imagine?
Like in the ad.
Do you see what I mean?
But why not?
Why not ?
It's wonderful.
A kind of pride,
a source of pride.
And as Dany said,
It's wonderful because it's...
Our parents,
our dad,
Our mother lives within us.
And then,
It has materialized.
I think it's good.
I think.
Without that,
it would have completely fallen into ruin.
It was already in ruins.
I hope they're not collecting all of that with a wheelbarrow.
because it will take a while.
I'm glad it wasn't demolished.
and at the same time,
I'm happy because the site is listed.
So they are obliged to respect many things.
And that,
I'm proud of it.
because there is a trace of my dad that will remain there.
And it's a rehabilitation that I find very interesting.
And I think these buildings are part of our heritage.
of rocasm,
That's for sure.
but also part of France's heritage.
And it's great to be able to transform it on the other side.
It has nonetheless been useful in the lives of many people.
Unfortunately, too.
Many people have died.
But he played a part in history and I think it's great that there's a new life to it.
In Paris,
There are many buildings that used to be clinics.
places where many people died,
where many things happened,
and in many places in France as well.
And today,
It is used in a completely different way and nobody has a problem with it.
I'm not very sensitive.
But it should have been demolished and then maybe trees replanted.
to be modern.
We have no regrets because we came here enough times to experience what we did.
even if it was very little.
and also enjoy the setting and a little bit of that atmosphere.
It's true that it's a bit sad to see him in this state.
It's going to be good.
It will be restored.
But me,
I like it when it's like that.
The squatting aspect,
the side...
We feel full of freedom.
That's what's interesting.
I am very,
very sad.
It's a place I really like.
I know,
I think I know it by heart.
So we had to do it over a long period.
wide,
across.
At least today,
This is the last time.
I know this is the last time
Once I set foot there,
It makes me nostalgic.
The only thing that can disappoint me right now,
It's about seeing the state of this room.
To see that it has been cleared,
That's not a problem.
but to see that our platform is no longer there,
That's a shame.
There,
that's the regret,
It hurts a little.
You thought she'd still be here,
Could you explain?
That's it.
To get on it or even just to see it again,
to see her one last time,
Because this will be the last time I come here.
And afterwards I don't even think I know what will become of this room.
And I don't want to know.
I want it to stay the way it is.
Even the image there is way too much.